Leah: Risk is often defined as an
event or activity that could have
a positive or negative outcome.
When doing something that involves
risk we often have to weigh up if the
potential reward is worth the risk!
Just think of some of those risky
activities like ‘skydiving’ or
‘swimming with sharks’ to something
as simple as ‘crossing the road’!
In all cases we have to identify
the risks and minimise them.
This is risk management!
Chris: So, what do we
mean by risk management?
In business risk management can be
defined as the process used to ‘identify,
assess and control threats to the
organisations financial stability’.
In coding we are referring to a ‘potential
situation arising that can have a
direct impact on a projects progress’.
Leah: Some potential risks may seem
rather extreme such as a ‘global
pandemic’, ‘terrorist attack’ or ‘war’!
however in today’s world these are
becoming more plausible as we all know!
But on the whole, all projects will have
more realistic risks attached such as,
project failure, too much time spent
on the project, overspend on budget
or possibly a poor-quality product.
Chris: The role of the project manager is
to identify the major risk factors that
may affect the project, evaluate these,
and prioritise them, and then plan how
these risks can be managed or mitigated.
They are also responsible for reviewing
and monitoring for any new risks that
might arise and updating all stakeholders.
Leah: Risks can be split up into two
types, Pure risks and Business risks.
Pure risks are extreme and often involve
the ultimate use of the software in
high-risk environments where failure of
the software may have dire consequences.
These don’t directly affect the
software development but have to be
considered regarding its deployment.
Chris: Business risks are more likely
to be encountered and often involve
risk associated with financial
aspects such as cost cutting
exercises and a lack of vision.
Every project has risks, but
software projects are special.
So, what are the potential risks that
could affect a projects delivery?
Let’s take a look at the most common.
Leah: Experience
A business risk may involve using less
experienced developers to save money.
This lack of experience could affect the
quality and deadline for the project.
However, the developer may rise to the
challenge and proves to be an asset and of
greater value in this and future projects.
Chris: Time and costs
Time estimates need to be realistic.
If a project team struggles to
meet the deadlines, quality could
suffer, which means work may need
to be redone and more delays.
In software development the
largest expense is usually
tied to the developers’ time.
So, If the time estimates are out
then so will be the cost estimates.
As costs pile up, stakeholders,
primarily management, may start
to lose faith, putting pressure
on for completion, resulting in
errors, lost time, and lost money!
Leah: Scope
Scope is the agreed body of work
that the project will capture.
‘Scope creep’, also called ‘mission
creep’, can occur when stakeholders
begin to sneak in changes that circumvent
the identified change request system
and time and cost are affected.
Scope changes may also stem from
the project team not having a clear
understanding of what’s considered
‘in scope’ and what’s ‘out of scope’.
Scope changes should be avoided unless
absolutely necessary but should always be
reflected in the time and cost estimates.
Chris: Feasibility
some projects are unrealistic in
regard to scope, schedule, and budget.
It’s the project manager’s job
to identify this unfeasibility
or face the consequences.
Leah: Quality
what good is a project if it’s
completed on time and on budget
but the software is full of bugs,
errors, and crashes all the time?
Chris: Stakeholder expectations.
title on screen
You must remember to maintain
communication channels.
Failure to ensure that the
project is moving in alignment
with stakeholder expectations can
risk not meeting their vision.
Leah: Human Resources
Knowledgeable technical resources
are always in great demand.
You may run the risk of your top
developers being recruited by other
firms therefore it’s important
to consider employee retention
strategies to mitigate this.
Technical accuracy.
Chris: If your project team
doesn’t have the skills to deliver
the project this is a risk.
The project team must be trained
and developed in order to reach
the project conclusion that you
and the stakeholder are expecting.
Leah: As well as these potential risks
there is also the risk that, if your
project is something that has never been
attempted before, you risk suffering
from the first-time, first-use penalty.
This penalty basically means that
because it’s never been done before
there is a higher risk of facing problems
you couldn’t possibly anticipate.